All I want to say to all of you is thank you very much, you've been great.
我最后想说的是，我十分感谢大家的支持，你们都是好人
Thank you, for everything you've given us in Japan.
感谢你们，让我们在日本享受了一段好时光
And thank you, really, you're the representatives of the whole world
然后呢，真心感谢你们，你们是我们所遇到的人中
as far as we're concerned.
最好的那几位
Thank you and God bless you for everything you've ever given us.
感谢你们，让上帝保佑你们和你们所给予我们的一切美好
And, this is the last night... The end.
还有，这是我们在一起的最后一晚了......一切都结束了:-(
God blessing. Thanks a lot. Good night
上帝保佑你们，感谢你们。晚安！
I didn't think Machine Head, at the time, was anything special.
在当时，我不认为 Machine Head 有啥特别的
It was Made In Japan, that threw it into the stratosphere.
实际上，是 Made In Japan 才让它火的
We did the same songs, on stage
我们只是在舞台上把专辑里的歌都演了一遍
and it seemed to take off that much bigger than Machine Head.
然后这居然就比 Machine Head 更火了
It's a beautiful snapshot of the band in all its glory.
这张专辑是我们乐队最漂亮的一出
Firing off each other working it out, live on stage.
大家很快地做出来，并上台演出
On the night.
就在一夜之间
And then, people started to break down.
然后，大家就开始为此疯狂
'72, I think we made, two albums, six US tours.
记得1972年，我们录了两张专辑，在美国巡演了六次
Something happened. Ritchie and Ian Gillan agreed to disagree.
然后就出事了，Blackmore和Gillan开始干架了:-(
I wrote a letter saying I was going to leave.
我给他们写下了辞职信
No-one said anything, so I assumed they wanted me to leave.
没有任何人说啥，所以我想我还是卷铺盖走人吧
It was just pressure pressure, pressure
在那时，整个情况就是压力，压力，和压力
and that's exactly why that split happened.
这也就是为啥我们拆伙了
We started in '68, Jon Lord and myself, and we put the band together
我们1968年创建了这个乐队，和Jon Lord一起
and I don't think we quite knew what direction that we had.
我们当时并不清楚我们的方向
Aehh, we kind of uhmm... flim flammed around in certain areas.
额，我们当时就像是......仅仅在一片小区域内燃烧的火焰
I think the first album was a recording of everything we'd learnt.
我认为第一张专辑仅仅是把我们所知的全都录了进去
I don't think we had anything else. I think that was it.
然后好像就没啥了，应该就是这样了
Aehh... couple of original bits and pieces and then quite a lot of covers.
额......一些原创歌曲和超级多的翻唱
The highs were the interaction that, uhmm... Ritchie, Jon and I found, we each other
好的方面在于我们间的交流......Blackmore，Lord和我
musically... and personally.
在音乐和个性方面找到了共性
We had a great time.
我们当时相处得不错
Uhmm, the lows were... learning very quickly that the... balance of the band.
然后坏的方面是......我们很快意识到，当时
personnel, couldn't go as far as it really needed to.
的乐队因为成员风格问题，不可能发展得更远
As we were staggering into 1969 Ritchie and I, particularly
当我们在1969年时还在艰难发展时，黑多多和我
realised that the band was, in danger of not being quite what we'd
意识到乐队正处于偏离我们正常轨道
seen it as in our minds.
的危险之中
It was kind of a little bit... pop.
这乐队有点......太流行了
There we are, like, really searching for an identity
然后我们就努力地寻求我们的定位
and that search goes on, pretty much through the first three albums.
然后我们一直在寻求，贯穿了前三张专辑
A friend of mine had a singer in his band, it was Ian Gillan.
我的一个朋友介绍了他乐队的歌手，Ian Gillan
So we tried out Ian. He had the scream, he had the look
所以我们面试了他，他能喊到天，颜值也不错
and that's why in 1970 we were on our way.
而这就是为什么1970年时我们开始上道了
Good morning. And how are you?
早上好啊！感觉如何？
Then, of course, In Rock came out, you know, and that became
然后，很自然地，In Rock出版了，你们都知道，然后
a phenomenon in the British charts in the top ten for over a year.
它就火遍了英国，在排行榜前十的位置上待了一年
It hit a chord with the British youth and Europe.
它迎合了英国年轻人和欧洲年轻人的激情
When we saw what In Rock had done, it was a calling card.
当我们看到In Rock完工的时候，我感受到他就是我们的名片
It said: this is Deep Purple.
他上面写着：我们就是Deep Purple
Everybody in the band was absolutely behind it
每个人都为专辑的制作作出了贡献
and that lasted pretty much into the Machine Head era.
并且这个状况一直延续到Machine Head的制作
Deep Purple In Rock stayed in the charts for over a year.
Deep Purple In Rock 在排行榜上待了超过一年
Big success to follow.
这之后我们还要更上一层楼
I think there was a feeling of: what do we do next?
我们当时就很迷茫：接下来我们要做什么？
How do we top that?
我们如何超越这个成功？
Fireball, there was a kind of certain intimidation going on
Fireball, 这个名字体现出我们的影响力（威胁）有多大
and by the time it was finished I think we were a little tired.
当我们完成这张专辑的时候，我们身心俱疲
Fireball was lots of fun, but it was a little more introvert.
做Fireball时我们确实很欢乐，但也把我们搞得有点社恐
And there's still some great tracks on it, but it didn't fire up
当然这张专辑里也有好歌，但是它没有
the imagination of the public the way that In Rock did.
像我们想的一样火起来，没有达到 In Rock 的地步
Fireball, it's a troublesome... album because, to me
Fireball，这张专辑是张很尴尬的专辑，因为
you couldn't have had Fireball without In Rock.
对我而言，如果没有In Rock ，就不可能Fireball
But you couldn't have Machine Head without Fireball, so it sits
但是要是没有Fireball，你不可能有Machine Head
very nicely as part of those three
所以这张专辑正好夹在这两座大山的中间:-(
really... good rock albums.
The success that In Rock and not quite so much Fireball
In Rock很成功，但是Fireball就没有
gave us, allowed us to say: "OK, the next time round, we're going to get
那么成功了，我们就在想：”好吧，我们来这么做
a situation where once we've got the sound, three weeks
只要有人想出旋律的话，几周之内我们
"we've got the songs together we just record them," you know?
就写好歌曲，攒好后就赶紧录，明白了吧？
And that's what we did with Machine Head.
我们就是这么录的Machine Head
Although we were wildly successful
尽管我们已经十分成功了
Deep Purple In Rock and Fireball
在发行In Rock和Fireball之后
uhmm... we actually hadn't made much money
额......我们实际上没有赚到很多的钱
because... we were paying back the management for...
因为我们当时得把钱给为我们乐队
having funded the band for so many years.
投资了许多钱的经纪人们
So despite all that success, you know, we needed to makes money.
所以我们尽管很成功，但是你明白，我们急需赚钱
In 1971, the law changed.
1971年的时候，法规变了
与 Richard Bagehot 的采访录音
Deep Purple公司的经理与律师
If a recording is done overseas, so long as the overseas derived income
如果一张唱片是在英国本土外录制的话，那么由此得来的一切收益
wasn't remitted into the UK it wasn't taxed in the UK.
只要不往英国汇款，你就不会被上税我们
What happened was that the boys had to become tax exiles.
当时就是这些孩子们想要逃税
That is a process which saved a huge amount of money.
这个过程确实帮助我们省了好多的钱
We had an accountant at the time called Bill Reid
我们那时有个会计，叫做Bill Reid
a brilliant guy, and he cooked up this scheme.
他脑袋瓜子很溜，然后他策划了整个计划
He said: "Look, if you write songs and record them
他说：“同志们，如果你们在国外写歌
"outside of the country, you won't be taxed English tax
录歌，你们就不会为此在英国上税
"you're only taxed on what you earn in England."
你们仅需为你们在英国挣到的钱上税就行了。”
And we travelled the Continent so it wasn't a big problem for us to do that.
然后我们就去欧洲大陆了，对我们来说，这不是事
We took specialist tax advice that in order for the boys to get
我们征询了许多税收专家的意见，让他们可以
the benefit of whatever they might do in the future, they would
在将来做任何事的时候都可以由此收益，他们必须
have to have an employment as opposed to a partnership.
要和公司有签约，而不是合作关系
As it was considered that their next album, which they had yet to record
正如我们所想，他们的下一张专辑，也就是当时他们还没有录制
or even write, was going to be the biggest that they would have had
甚至于还没写的专辑，将要获得前所未有的成功
yet because of the rising success in album sales
因为他们名声越来越大，销量越来越好
that we would institute the employment regime by having a company
那么我们计划为我们的雇员建立一个公司
which was an English company
这是个英国公司
but it employed the artists only for their overseas activities.
但是这个公司只雇在海外活动的艺术家
And the next album which they did, which was Machine Head
然后他们录的下一张专辑，就是Machine Head
made that a very wise decision.
这就让这个决定十分明智了
So we thought we'd record an album under studio conditions
那么我们就想在表演场地中
but in a live venue.
建立一个录音室的环境，来录制专辑
Claude Nobs was the instigator of us going to Switzerland
Claude Nobs 怂恿我们去瑞士
and Claude said that he could set us up with something over there
他说他可以把我们安顿个地方来录专辑
which was the Casino to record at the Casino.
那个地方是个娱乐场
Under the new regime and under their employment contracts
在全新的公司和全新合约的要求下
had to record overseas. The question then would be, where to go.
我们必须在海外录专辑。那么问题来了，我们去哪录呢？
And the band and Tony and Jon looked around and spoke to Claude Nobs
然后整个乐队和他们的经纪人找了一圈，最后找到了Claude Nobs
who was a promoter on the Continent.
当时他是欧洲大陆上的演唱会筹办人
Claude Nobs, our friend from Montreux, he did the jazz festival.
Claude Nobs，我们在Montreux的朋友，他筹办了一个爵士乐音乐节
He said, "We've got tonnes of space here.
他说：“我们这有好多地方能用
You can do it here.
你可以在这录
We'll find a place in the Casino which is closed for the winter.
我们找到了一个赌场，这地方冬天关门
Everyone knows the story.
然后就是 纪 实 文 学 警告
大家都说，流行乐是现在音乐消费者社会的创造
这话没错，但是在此之下是许多优秀乐队的辛勤创造
首先是专业素养，然后才是音乐素养
那么这就是我们想给Montreux带来的东西
That was probably the best times of Purple back then
回想起来，这也许是Deep Purple当时最好的时候
and when we arranged to go to Switzerland to do this album
然后我们组织好，去瑞士录这张专辑
it was just a fantastic time you know?
你知道吗，那时可真是好时候啊！
Unfortunately, the Casino burned down
可惜的是，那个赌场被烧毁了:-(
but out of that sprang the song, of course.
而这就是那首歌的灵感来源
Without that, there would have been no Smoke On The Water.
没有那次事故的话，你就听不到Smoke On The Water了
Why did you go to Switzerland to record Machine Head?
为什么你们要去瑞士录Machine Head？
Several reasons. One being it's a great place to be, Montreux.
原因很多。第一，Montreux那个地方很不错
We know a lot of people in Montreux. And it was a nice place to go.
我们认识很多那里的朋友，而且十分宜人
The second, because we used The Rolling Stones' mobile unit
第二，因为我们用了滚石乐队的移动录音工作室
and that was in the South of France and it was easy to trundle it up to Switzerland.
那个东西是在法国南部，所以将其运到瑞士就很容易了
Humm... And thirdly, money reasons tax reasons. It's... It's...
额，第三嘛，就是资金问题，税收问题了。这个就......
You can avoid paying some tax on your albums, on your royalties
你可以不用为你录的专辑上税，也不用交版税
if you've made the album out of the country.
只要你在国外录制专辑的话
It's a very complicated deal but it's not illegal.
这个过程十分复杂，但是这个不违法
I mean, tax people know about it but it's just if you want to take
我是说，纳税人都知道，但是如果你想由此
advantage of it, you have to record outside the country.
获益的话，你必须得在国外录制专辑
And also, we did it in two weeks
还有，我们花了两周录了这个
aheh, where normally we take three or four months over an album
呃，一般我们要花三四周录制一张专辑
on and off, but we just had a concentrated two weeks playing, you know
但是我们当时只是专注地花了两周录制
We'd written all the songs and we just went in and recorded.
我们写完了歌，然后就进棚录制了
The Casino in Montreux, Switzerland
Montreux那里的赌场了
if you were doing a tour of Europe, you'd play there.
如果你在欧洲巡回演出过的话，你一定在那里演出过
And the guy who was organising it, Claude Nobs, said:
然后组织这件事的人，Claude Nobs，说
"Don´t put your gear in yet, because there's one more show before you can do it.
”你们先别进去，因为在这之前这里还有一个演出
"It's a matinee tomorrow afternoon, Frank Zappa
那是个日场，在下午三点
"And The Mothers. Three o'clock. Do you want to go?". "Sure."
是Frank Zappa and The Mothers的演出，你想去吗？”“那当然”
And about an hour into the show
在我们进场看演出后，大概一个钟头
someone fired a flare gun into the ceiling, which was made of...
有人向天花板打了一枪信号弹，那就很让人......
It was like a false ceiling, bamboo.
记得当时天花板掉了下来
And there wasn't much of a fire at first, but things came to
一开始倒也没多大火，但是演出停止了
a halt and everyone was ordered to leave the building.
大家都被要求离开这个赌场
And there was a little bit of a panic, but not bad.
记得当时有点混乱，但是还好
No-one was hurt strangely enough.
虽然很离谱，但是没有人受伤
And literally within five minutes or so, the place was an inferno.
然后大概五分钟后，这地方就被烧毁了
Fire!
着火了！
Probably go towards the exit, ladies and gentlemen.
女士们，先生们，请赶快离开这里！
我当时就在他舞台的旁边，记得他拿吉他砸碎了一个很大的窗户
然后他拿起麦克风，平静地说：“现在着火了，请大家平静地离开这里”
那里还有一个弓窗，向着游泳池方向
人们也没跳，只是很平静地走了出去
两分钟之后，大家全在看这个地方化成灰烬
有人就说：“你知道吗，Frank真的是结束演出的大师，看看这玩意！”
The fire had started in the ceiling
大火烧到天花板了
and it spread without anyone seeing it and it was a huge building
然后大火在人们没注意的时候越烧越大
it wasn't just a casino it was a venue
然后那个很大的赌场很快就烧成灰烬了:-(
that's where we were watching Zappa, there was a disco there
那里是Zappa演出的地方，是蹦迪的地方
bars, restaurants, a big casino, big convention facilities, so it was a
是享受美食的地方，还是个大赌场，大型会议场所
massive building and it was a wooden building and, bang, it just went up.
就这个非常大的建筑，轰的一下，就烧没了:-(
And the next morning, we went there and it was still smouldering.
转天早晨，我们去到那里，那里还在冒烟
It's amazing that no-one got hurt.
居然没人受伤，这很令我们惊讶
FRANK ZAPPA: We'd just started playing King Kong
FRANK ZAPPA: 我们当时刚开始 King Kong
but we were playing and in that part of King Kong, I stop the band
但是正当我们演奏当时那里着了 King Kong 时，我中止了演出
and so, obviously, there was a fire and a window in the back
因为，很明显地，那里着火了，然后那个后面的
a big window with maybe a 10 or 15-feet drop down.
大窗户，大概英尺还是15英尺高的，就掉下来了
They broke that and people were jumping out and aehh...
他们把那个窗户砸开来，人们就跳了出去
So, everybody got out.
反正大家全都出去啦
And Claude, bless him Claude was wonderful.
还有Claude，是啊，Claude是个不错的家伙呢
There's a photograph of Claude in Machine Head taken as the fire
Machine Head 内页中有一张 Claude 的照片
was raging and he came by the hotel to see us and the look
他在大火正在燃烧的时候来旅店看我们
on his face is evident in that picture, it's a wonderful picture.
这张图片就是证明，真是张很好的图片呢
I mean his future, his life was going up in flames and, bless him
我是说，他的未来，他的事业正在变得红火起来，然后，老天爷啊
he didn't think about that, he said:
但是他并没有想到这些，他说：
"I'm really worried about you what are you going to do?"
“我十分担心你们的录音计划，你们有啥想法吗？”
"We've got to find somewhere else."
"我们得找个其他的地方"
Montreux, then, it was a very small sleepy town, very upper class.
那时的Montreux是一个很小很安谧的小镇，十分高档
It was very quiet. I think there was one club, a couple of restaurants.
那个地方十分安静，我记得有一个俱乐部，几家饭馆
It had a lot of tea shops
还有很多卖茶的地方
lots of little old ladies going out in the afternoon for tea
很多老太太下午出来喝茶
and we're looking for somewhere where we can make
我们就得找个别的地方来
a lot of noise in the middle of the night.
在大半夜的时候能继续录音
That's a pretty tall order.
这个要求确实很高
Now, we only had a certain amount of time with the Stones' mobile.
当时，我们只能短暂地使用移动录音棚一段时间
Aehh... we started work in one place, which was a theatre in town.
额，我们最后找到个位置，那是个城里的剧院
Aehh... we did one track there and the police were hammering on the door
然后，我们仅仅录了一首歌，警察就上门了
we actually did the track about one or two in the morning
在花了一晚上排练，把设备准备好后
after spending all evening rehearsing and getting sounds and stuff so
我们当时在早晨录了一两首歌
we obviously couldn't use that place and we got a little bit desperate.
很明显地我们不能再用那个地方，把我们闹得很不愉快
Well, it was chaos, I mean...
那时有点混乱，我的意思是
from being beautifully organised and arranged
本来计划得很好
we would record here, the truck would be here, the hotel was there
我们本可以在那里录音，移动录音棚也在，那个旅馆也没被烧
all of a sudden, you've got nowhere to record cos it's a bunch of ashes.
但就是突然之间，你那里也去不了，因为各种各样的烦心事
But you've still got the expense of the hotel, you've still got
但是你还是给旅馆住宿费，你还得给贾大嘴
the truck there that's got to be paid, everybody's over there.
移动录音室的租赁费，当然，还有很多人的
What do you do? You find somewhere else to do it, you know
你还能怎么办？你必须找个别的地方
We looked at barns farms, hotel basements.
我们找了农场的谷仓，旅馆的地下室
Various places
好多地方呢
and I think it took about five or six days before we found the Grand Hotel
我记得大约花了五六天才找到Grand Hotel
which was closed. It was winter, it was November.
当时那里关门，因为当时是11月，是冬天
Machine Head to me was...
对我而言，Machine Head
I had realised how simple and easy it was to make a good record
我到那时才明白录张好唱片是多么的简单和容易
humm... without all the trappings, without the headaches.
没必要多么修饰自己的音乐，也不必硬着头皮想旋律
We made that record in three weeks and three days
我们当时花了三周又三天来录专辑
and it was great substance, great record and it was done, out.
然后这个质量很高的，伟大的专辑就诞生了
And, to me, that represented how a record should be made.
对我而言，这个过程教我如何录制一张好专辑
Quick and to the point.
快速并且直击重点
It's interesting the way a band looks at its material
当选单曲的时候，我们选我们录制
when it comes to singles.
的歌曲的时候很有趣
Because we weren't really...
因为我们当时就......
It goes without saying, we weren't really a singles band
怎么说呢，我们不是一个单曲型乐队
it wasn't the kind of thing that we felt comfortable putting
我们对于将我们的创意录进
the material into single form it didn't come easy to us.
一张单曲并不感冒，这个对于我们而言不太容易
But we were writing well by that time and I honestly thought that
不过我们当时写歌很在状态，说真的
we'd written a great single in Never Before.
我们自认为我们写了一个很好的单曲，Never Before
In fact, to the point that
实际上，在那个时候
when we sent it across to Warner Bros in the States
当我们把这个送到美国的华纳唱片时
aehh... we sent it with the indication that Never Before would be the single.
额，我们当时把Never Before作为单曲的消息送了出去
It came back with the comment
他们发了一条回信
"You must be joking. The hit is Smoke On The Water."
"你没开玩笑吧，大热门一定是Smoke On The Water"
To which we said:
我们当然回应为
"You must be joking, the hit is Never Before."
"你没开玩笑吧，大热门一定是Never Before"
We honestly didn't think that Smoke On The Water was hit material.
说真的，我们当时没有认为Smoke On The Water将是个大热门
How wrong can you be?
怎么会是这样呢？
Machine Head, Deep Purple's new album
Machine Head, Deep Purple 的全新专辑
in your record shop now on Purple Records.
正在各大唱片店热销，Purple Records发行
Where else?
还不快买
Machine Head came out and it was a reasonable hit... people liked it.
Machine Head 出版了，也跟我们想的一样火了，人们很喜欢它
But it wasn't till Made In Japan came out that people actually
但直到 Made In Japan 发行后，人们才真正地
absorbed it and registered that it was a good record.
接受它，并认为这是张好唱片
'We did the same songs... on stage'
'我们是......在舞台上把歌曲又演奏了一遍'
and it seemed to take off that much bigger than Machine Head.
看上去这个效果要比Machine Head专辑里的更好
It's nice to be here.
我们来到这里很开心
We've had a nice time over the last few days
最近几天我们在这里玩得很开心
I hope you enjoy yourselves.
希望大家听得开心
If we could have a little bit more atmosphere on the lights
后台，如果你们能把灯光气氛调整得更好
we'd appreciate it.
我们会很满意的
'I didn't think Machine Head
我不认为Machine Head
'at the time, was anything more special than Fireball'
在那时，比Fireball或者In Rock
or In Rock.
强到哪里去
Uhmm, and in fact, it wasn't really until we did Made In Japan
嗯，实际上，直到Made In Japan这张
the live album, that it really came to life.
现场专辑的发行后，这张专辑才生动了起来
Yeah, it was a big hit
是的，这是张热门专辑
but, it was Made In Japan that threw it into the stratosphere.
但是，Made In Japan的发行使这张专辑直接冲上了天
Made In Japan started as an idea from the Japanese record company.
Made In Japan实际上一开始是日本唱片公司的主意
注：华纳唱片公司日本分公司 Warner Bros. Pioneer Company
They said, "We want a live album, Japan only."
他们说：”我们要录张现场专辑，只是日本现场“
We hated the thought of live albums, strangely
我们当时很奇怪地，十分讨厌现场专辑的主意
for a band that was so good live.
即使我们现场表演地如此地好
We just thought "Maybe not."
我们当时就想：”这可不行。“
So, we said, "Only if it only ever comes out in Japan."
所以，我们就说：”行，只要这张专辑只在日本发行就好“
Thus the title.
这就是专辑名称的由来了
Made In Japan, of course as a title was a joke
Made In Japan，当然是有点玩笑的意味在
because in England in the '50s, '60s, '70s
因为在上世纪中叶时的英国
if something was said to be "made in Japan"
如果有人说这个东西是”日本制造“
it was almost like it was second rate so, to us, it was like
那就意味着这个东西是次等品，所以，对我们而言
Made in China: 哇，我终于找到我小时候的同类了
"Oh, yes, just made in Japan"
“哦，好吧，咱就在日本录吧
and it would only ever come out in Japan.
反正这个只在日本发行。”
And we eventually heard it
我们最后听了一遍
and realised that we had something rather wonderful.
发现里面有某种神奇的魅力
Back in the early '70s...
回到70年代早期
live albums were viewed as sort of budget albums.
现场专辑会被认为是低成本专辑
They were viewed as if you had nothing better to do.
他们会被看作是当你们没有什么好主意的时候（你录制的专辑）
They were...not considered a proper album.
他们不被认为是一张正规专辑
Studio albums were proper albums.
录音室专辑是正规专辑
Live albums were things you did on the side.
现场专辑就相当于次要专辑了
We were kind of wary of doing that
我们对这件事十分厌恶
because we'd been a pretty heavily bootlegged band
因为多年以来我们们的现场
for a couple of years.
一直被人盗录，然后去卖
There was a Japanese record company that wanted to record the live album.
然后日本的唱片公司想让我们录一张现场专辑
We said: "No, we're not doing that."
我们当时就说：”不，我们才不录呢“
They kept on insisting. We said:
他们非得让我们录，我们就说：
"OK, we'll do it in certain conditions.
“好吧，你们要是满足这些条件，我就录
"A: it only comes out in Japan."
首先，这张专辑只能在日本发行
"B: it doesn't come out at all if we don't like it."
其次，如果我们对录制结果不满意的话，我们不会同意发行的
"And C: we mix it and have our own engineer record it."
最后：这张专辑必须由我们来混音，由我们的工程师来录。”
Excellent musicians. What can you say about them?
他们确实是十分厉害的音乐家，无可挑剔
Martin Birth：制作人 工程师
They were the best at what they did
他们当时做得很好
without a shadow of a doubt.
没有一点可以抱怨的地方
I think they influenced a lot of groups over the years.
我认为他们这么多年来影响了很多乐队
You know, I went to my first Deep Purple concert in 1973.
比如说我，我1973年第一次去听Deep Purple的演唱会
February, 1973. It blew my mind. I'd never seen energy at that level.
1973年2月时听的，他震撼了我，我当时从来没有听过这么有气场的音乐
Lars Ulrich：Metallica的鼓手
I'd never seen performance I'd never seen personality
我从未见过这样的演出，我从未见过这样富有个性的演出
like, it was the biggest thing I'd ever seen.
就像是，我当时认为这是我见过的最大的演出了
When I was growing up as a kid, I grew up in California
我小的时候是在加利福尼亚长大的
Matt Sorum：枪花前鼓手，1990-1997
but the first album... that I really got into was, aehh, Made In Japan.
但是我第一张拥有的专辑是Made In Japan
Which was a double live album.
是张双碟专辑
You know, in the States, Made In Japan was probably one of the highlights.
James Hetfield：Metallica的吉他手和主唱
你知道的，在美国，Made In Japan是当时的一个热门
All the hits that came through America were the ones that we got.
所有火遍全美的单曲都是从这张专辑里挑出来的
That was another brilliant album that was recorded under
这张专辑是又一张传奇，因为这是在
Colin Hart：巡演管理员 1971-2001
really strange and extreme conditions, you know?
十分尴尬和极端的环境下录制的
I remember Martin Birch was out.
我记得 Martin Birch 后来出去了
We put the control room backstage
我们把控制室放在了幕后
so he had no physical eye contact with the band.
这样他们就不会和乐队成员有眼神交流
It was all just listening. We found that really strange.
就只是听着录专辑，就很尴尬
But that turned out...
但是最终成果呢......
..fantastic, for the time. Brilliant album.
在那时看来，十分精彩，十分精彩的专辑
Maybe Ritchie and Ian weren't getting on well off stage
也许黑多多和Ian Gillan在台下相处得不是太好
注：就离谱，黑多多相中的Gillan，也许他们俩的关系就跟可基大学里谈恋爱的情侣一样吧:-P
but on stage there was still a massive important
但是在台上，他们之间的配合
amount of chemistry.
还是很好的
I never saw either Zeppelin or Purple when I was a kid
在我小的时候，我从未看过Led Zeppelin或者是Deep Purple的演出
Bruce Dickinson：Iron Maiden主唱
when they were in their heyday when they were all firing away.
无论是他们如日中天之时，还是他们没那么火的时候
I never saw Purple or Zeppelin.
反正在那时我从来都没有看过
So all I had to go on was their respective live things.
所以我只能通过他们的标志性现场录音来了解他们了
On that score, Purple kicked their pants.
在这样的情况下，Deep Purple给我留下了很深的印象
I think that Made In Japan might be really, for a lot of people
我认为Made In Japan也许真的是，对于很多人来说
the quintessential Deep Purple record, especially from that time.
是Deep Purple最有代表性的专辑了，尤其是在那时
One of the greatest, if not the greatest live album ever recorded.
这可以说是有史以来最伟大，但不是十分伟大的现场专辑之一
Of course, Martin Birch who worked with Purple
当然，和Deep Purple在各个方面都合作过的
on just about everything, was our producer in Maiden for many years.
Martin Birth，也为我们Iron Maiden当了很多年的制作人
So you'd sit down over a few beers and talk to Martin
所以我们当时很自然地喝了几口啤酒，和Martin交谈了几句
and you'd get the lowdown. You'd think, "Wow, it really was live.
然后你就知道了几个幕后故事，你就会想：“天啊，这真的就是
"There were no overdubs. It was as was."
纯现场录音，没有后期补录，一切都是本色。”
注：KISS的Alive现场专辑因为录制条件太差，后期除了鼓声外全部是后期补录
That's what makes it even more incredible
这就让这张专辑更加令人难以置信了
it was done in eight track or something.
这些东西就是直接录在八轨磁带上啥的
Every single live version, every single recording is different
每一个现场版本的歌，每一段录音都是不同的
so if you hear three nights in Japan
所以你要是把这1972年8月在日本的三晚的
注：1993年，EMI发行了这三晚的完整录音
in August '72, Strange Kind Of Woman
三场现场录音都听下来的话，你会发现Strange Kind of Woman
Child Of Time, whatever, they're all different from each other.
Child Of Time，还有很多，他们都稍微有些不同
Ritchie plays different solos Ian sings different phrases
黑多多弹的solo不同，Gillan唱的段落也不同
Ian Paice plays different drum fills.
Ian Paice即兴鼓点敲的也很不同
It's the coolest thing cos you never know exactly what's coming next.
这可真是极好的，因为你永远不知道接下来会有什么:-)
I think Made In Japan is possibly
我认为Made In Japan或许是
Peter Makowski：记者
one of the greatest live rock albums ever made.
有史以来最伟大的现场专辑之一了
and, I'll tell you why.
现在咱来说说为嘛
Firstly, because there was nothing like it that ever came out before.
首先，因为之前从来没有一个人这么干过
Secondly, it showed you the difference between a band
其次，这张专辑向你展示了一个乐队
in the studio and a band live.
现场演出和录音室录制时的差别
We recorded three shows.
我们当时录了三场演唱会
By that time the anarchy that was happening on stage
在那时台上即兴演奏的疯狂
had coalesced into certain, you know...
逐渐融合成一股......怎么说呢
You do something on stage as on live.
你在台上演出时总得表演些什么
If it works, you tend to do it another night.
要是表演的好的话，你就会想在另一晚再演一次
So all these little bits and pieces of punctuation between the songs
那么歌曲之间或者段落之间的一小段即兴
and during the songs were becoming second nature to us.
演奏就成为我们的第二本能了
To me, that is one of the most missed things in rock 'n' roll
对于我而言，这就是这就是在舞台上表演时
the thing that it's about a moment up on stage.
你所缺少的摇滚因素
You don't know where it's going next.
你不知道接下来要演什么
The interplay between Ritchie and Gillan, for example.
让我以黑多多和Gillan在间隙即兴时的配合为例
Guitar, voice, guitar voice, that kind of the...
吉他演奏，人声高亢，交织在一起，感觉就很......
Jon and Ritchie thing.
Jon Lord和黑多多再配合
It was just pure good fortune that really
那时我们的状态是最好的
we recorded that album at really the peak of our performing abilities.
我们当时录制的专辑确实能代表我们的最高水平
Ritchie would solo until he didn't want to solo any more.
黑多多会一直solo直到他不再想solo了
and If you know what to look for, he'd turn around
如果你注意的话，他转个头
he'd raise his right hand.
伸出了他的右手
He'd look over at Ian Paice and then, within two or four bars
他看了一眼Ian Paice，然后Paice打四个小节
he'd go into the next part.
他们就进入下一部分了
A band on fire, I would say. A band absolutely at the top of its game.
要我说的话，这个乐队当时很火了，他们当时的状态是最好的
That's why I loved that album.
这就是为什么我很喜欢这张专辑
It's a beautiful snapshot of the band in all its glory playing live
这个是我们当时一起在晚上做现场演出时
firing off each other listening to each other
互相配合，互相聆听
working it out live on stage, on the night.
一起演奏出美妙旋律的美妙画面
Uhmm... it wasn't really until we got back to England and put the tapes on...
我们回到英国后，把磁带放了一下
They sound great.
听上去真不错
I mean maybe this should be out.
我想也许这个应该发行
By that time, the American label, Warner Brothers
在那时，我们在美国的发行商，华纳唱片公司
weren't interested in a live album.
对现场专辑并不感冒
They wanted the next studio album which was, Who Do We Think We Are.
他们很想发行我们的下一张专辑，Who Do We Think We Are
And, you know... back then you don't think you're going to last very long.
然后呢，在那时我不认为咱们乐队能走得更远
You think you're only as good as your last record.
你认为你的能力只能够录你的最后一张专辑了
but if you're lucky, you can get another couple of years out of it
但是你要是幸运的话，你可以再得到几年的合同
and then, who knows what?
然后呢，谁知道呢？
One of the great Purple classics is on Who Do We Think We Are:
Deep Purple 的金曲之一就在 Who Do We Think We Are
Woman From Tokyo.
Woman From Tokyo
It's made under very difficult circumstances.
当时的情况十分困难
We had In Rock then we had Fireball then Machine Head.
我们已经做了In Rock，Fireball，Machine Head
You know, then we had Who Do We Think We Are.
然后，就是这张Who Do We Think We Are
Again, a little more introvert.
当然，我们之间更自闭了
A lot more difficult to record
录制起来更加困难了
which I think is probably the problem with Who Do We Think We Are.
也许这就是录制Who Do We Think We Are时最大的问题
We were in a villa just outside Rome, which had been chosen for us
我们当时在罗马城外一个别墅录的
to record in because it had a wonderful room to record.
我们觉得那个地方适合录音，就选了那里
What they hadn't done was measure the size of an archway
但是他们当时没有把拱道尺寸给测量出来
through which the mobile unit would have had to have gone
而拱道是用来过移动工作室的
to make it nice and easy. The mobile unit wouldn't fit under the archway, so...
让其过来时容易些，可惜移动工作室尺寸和拱道的不相配:-(
cables had to be brought in specially. Special long cables.
所以我们还得定制线缆，超级长的线缆:-(
We staggered through, we got an album out of it.
我们争吵不断，我们还录了张专辑
So Made In Japan was really the Machine Head record.
所以说Made In Japan实际上就是Machine Head的配套
And, if we waited till after Who Do We Think We Are
如果我们要在Who Do We Think We Are发行后发行这个
it would have been out of date
那这个就会过时了
so we, really wanted to put it out there.
所以我们一定要在那时发行
Which they eventually did, but only because...
他们最终发行了，但这是因为
our management started importing copies into the States.
我们的管理层在往美国出口这张专辑
Realised, uhmm... Warner Brothers realised that theywere losing out.
华纳唱片公司最终意识到他们错过了一座大金山
Who Do We Think We Are. I think on that album... It wasn't that good.
说到Who Do We Think We Are，我觉得这张专辑不是那么好
It started off OK.
一开始录制时还行
But there were cracks showing
但是成员间开始离心
I think Ritchie and Ian weren't getting on too well.
我认为当时黑多多和Gillan关系不是太好
Uhmm... I don't know why... that happened.
然后......后来的事情我就不明白了
But, yeah, the cracks were starting to appear.
但是，当时他们之间的不满开始显现了
Somewhere between Fireball and Who Do We Think We Are
在录制Fireball和Who Do We Think We Are之间的某段时间
going through the Machine Head period
当然，这是贯穿整个Machine Head录制时段的
Ritchie and Ian Gillan agreed to disagree.
黑多多和Gillan两口子开始干架了
Something happened. I'm not sure what it was.
就这么发生了，我都不知道为啥
I'm not sure, actually, that either of them could now iterate exactly
真的，我都不知道啥情况，他们两个在相同的事情
what it was that went down between the two of them, but something did.
上天天争论，消磨了两人的关系，但是最终还是发生了什么
We'd done about as much as we could do with that kind of rock
我们已经在发展这种摇滚乐的事情上做了够多了
as far as I could see.
就我目前所知道的
My idea was that there was far too much talent in the band
我认为我们的乐队各个成员天赋过剩
注：Beatles and King Crimson 直呼内行
for it to remain static.
很难保持现在的这个状态
I thought we were compromising ourselves.
我认为我们现在正在向自己妥协
I thought we were losing our integrity.
我还认为我们没有了骨气（？）
My decision to leave the band was in '72.
我在1972决定退出乐队
Confused, young unfocused, frustrated.
只是因为少年的迷茫和沮丧
The thing that a lot of people forget is that he was not fired, he left.
有很多没注意到的是，他不是被炒了，他是辞职了
I mean, he wrote us a letter saying that he no longer agreed with the...
他当时写了一封信，说他对目前乐队发展的方向
direction that the band was taking.
不太赞同
I do have to say this, that I think
我必须说，我真心认为
if our management had understood
要是我们的经纪人们能够理解
that it was actually a cry for help
他是在寻求理解和帮助的话
aehh... that he would not have been out of the band.
他大概就不会离开乐队的吧
Something had been thrown into the pot to change the formula.
可是真的，这封信改变了一切
Google机器翻译：往锅里扔了一些东西来改变配方。
I don't know what it was
我不知道这是怎么了
but it seemed to be not the Deep Purple that I'd joined in '69.
但很明显，这个Deep Purple不是我在1969年加入的Deep Purple了
It's not the band it was. You suddenly think, well, I don't know.
这不是以前那个乐队了，你很快就会认为......怎么说呢
I've always made my decisions on the basis of...
我一直都是基于
I've got to be enjoying what I'm doing.
“我干这件事情是不是高兴”的原则来做决定的
I didn't know how to fix it, so I thought I'd quit.
我不知道该怎么办，所以我退出乐队了
Broke my heart at the time. Didn't want that to happen one bit. I was...
在那时我很伤心，完全不知道该怎么办。我当时就
Even through the difficulties with Ritchie and Gillan...
尽管黑多多和Gillan俩口子经常吵架
I still thought we had a marvellous band.
我还是觉得我们是一个十分成功的大乐队
In the band, it was widely presumed
乐队里面，我们当时觉得
that Ritchie was going to leave
黑多多也要离开
and take Paice with him.
还要拉上Paice
Gillan had written his letter of resignation...
Gillan 写完辞职信后
..which left Jon and I.
那就只剩下Jon Lord和我了
Ritchie is one of these guys
黑多多是那种
I think he's always looking for something new.
我个人认为，是一个十分喜欢追寻新奇东西的人
And, unknown to us, he'd been secretly jamming
而且，我们当时还不知道的是
with Phil Lynott from Thin Lizzy.
黑多多正和Thin Lizzy的Phil Lynott秘密Jamming
注：Jam 即即兴演奏，一般是用来磨合关系并创作旋律的
He wanted to do a three piece, I think.
我想他应该是想写三组音乐片段吧
I wanted to form a band with Phil Lynott from Thin Lizzy.
我当时想和Thin Lizzy的Phil Lynott组队
I said to Ian Paice: "Let's have a three piece
我和Ian Paice说：“咱们来写三组音乐片段
of aehh... "and we'll play some kind of Hendrix blues stuff."
然后......咱来点Hendrix味的蓝调"
Our two managers, Tony Edwards and John Coletta
一天晚上，我们乐队的两个经纪人，Tony Edwards和John Coletta
summoned Jon and I to a restaurant one night in London and said:
把 Jon Lord 和我叫到伦敦的一个餐馆，并且说
"This is crazy.
”现在情况太疯狂了！
"The band's breaking up
乐队正在分崩离析
"and you're the biggest band in the world right now.
可你们现在是全世界最大，最成功的乐队啊！
"Maybe you can persuade Paice to stay with you
也许你们能说服Paice留在乐队
"and we'll get a new lead singer and a new guitarist and carry on."
然后咱再找个新的主唱和吉他手来继续咱们的事业。”
And aehh... painful as that was to understand, why not?
这对我们而言，就......太难以理解了，对吧？
We said, "Yeah let's do that."
我们答应道：“好吧，咱先这么干。”
Yeah, our first job, Jon and I was to talk Paice into staying.
然后，我们的第一件事是，我们俩去说服Paice留在乐队
At that point Ian was involved.
在那时Ian Paice有点让人难以理解
He said: "You know what?
他说：你想想
What would you want to stay in Deep Purple
你要是留在Deep Purple，那该多好啊
Ian's leaving, what's the problem with the band?
Ian Gillan虽然走了，但是乐队本身没有什么问题啊
Why won't you stay with Purple?
你为何不留在Deep Purple呢？
I said: "Well, OK.
我说：那行
"I would expect Roger maybe to leave
只要Roger Glover离开就行
注：我觉得黑多多就是把对Gillan的气都撒在了Glover上，没有想过归队的事情
"because I wasn't particularly into what he was doing."
因为我对他的风格不太满意
I said: "But that's not fair because Roger's done nothing wrong.
他说：这不公平啊，Roger并没有做错什么啊
注：个人认为他口误了，应该是Paice说的
"I'd rather leave the band
你这话说着，让我都想要离队
"get another thing going than fire somebody who's done nothing wrong."
找点别的事情干而不是把什么也没做错的人给开除了
The following... I think in January '73, with the Scandinavian tour
接下来，记得是1973年1月，我们在北欧巡演
we got Paice in the dressing room afterwards and said
我们演出后在换衣室叫住了Paice，跟他说
"Look, stick with us, we'll get a new guitarist, a new singer."
听着，跟我们在一起吧。我们回来再找个主唱和吉他手
And he said: he'd think about it.
他当时说他正在考虑
You have to remember, I was very much a kid then.
你们得先了解一点，我当时的思维和小孩子无异
I was a kid in a candy store. My life was one big party.
我当时就像糖果店里的孩子，生活就像是个很大的派对
I really didn't worry about what was going to happen
我对接下来发生的事情完全不知
the next day the next gig.
明天会怎样啊，下一场演出会如何啊
I mean... that sort of uhmm, responsibility was taken on by Ritchie and Jon
我当时认为这些事应该由黑多多和Jon Lord考虑
who were a little further along life's highway than I was.
因为这和我想的人生道路不太一样
We did a Japanese tour. Then two American tours.
我们在日本巡演了一次，然后是美国的两次
And, it was on the second American tour that I realised...
然后，在第二次美国巡演的时候我意识到
..that no-one was talking to me.
没人跟我说话了:-(
Ian said: "OK, we'll fire Roger if you're going to stay."
Ian Paice说：好的，你要留下来的话，我们就把Roger给炒了
And I... I felt really awkward.
当时我挺秃然的
黑多多：我就是一句气话，结果我不光害了Glover，我还得归队:-(
I said: "Em...OK."
我当时说：“......好吧”
It was a kind of weird feeling. I was kind of out in the cold.
我当时感觉很不好，就好像孙悟空被唐僧赶了出去
I couldn't put my finger on what was going on.
可是我没有花果山啊，我都不知道该咋办了
We were in Jacksonville, Florida.
我们当时在佛罗里达的Jacksonville
Came back to the motel we were staying in.
回到我们下榻的旅馆
I knocked on Tony Edwards' door, our manager at the time.
我敲开了Tony Edward的门，我们当时的经纪人
He said: "What do you want?" I said: "What's going on?"
他问：“来此贵干？”我反问：“现在是什么状况？”
He said: "Nothing."
他说：“一切照常。”
I said: "Something's going on."
我反驳道：“现在暗流涌动”
He said: "No no, no, no.
他否定地说：不是，真的一切照常
"Nothing's going on."
I said: "Well, I'm not leaving this room until you level with me."
我说：好的，除非你跟我说实话，否则我就在此赖上了
He said: "OK. They want you to leave the band."
他只好挑明了：好吧，他们想让你离队
"Why?" He said: "I don't know, that's the way it is.
“什么？”他接着说：“我也不知道为啥，但就是这样
"Ritchie's decided he'll stay with the band on the condition
黑多多同意留队，条件是你
"that you leave."
必须离队
Pretty hurtful thing to hear.
听上去确实很难受
Maybe I did the wrong thing, but I said: "Well...
也许我真干错了什么，但是我还是说：
you're not going to fire me.
好吧，你不会开除我的
"I'll keep my dignity and I'll leave of my own accord.
我坚持站好我的最后一班岗，然后我自行离开
"And why didn't anyone tell me this before?"
为啥他们之前没跟我说呢？
They said, "Because we wanted to finish the tour.
他们说：因为我们要完成巡演
"We didn't want you leaving in the middle of a tour."
我们不想让你在巡演半途就离队
*** them... I thought, them. I'll fulfill my duty. I'll be the gentleman here.
他们真是够该死的，我当时想。“我当然会尽我的职责，我会
"I'll fulfill my duties and then I'm gone."
很绅士地处理这些问题，我干完活就走
So the rest of that tour...
那么巡演的剩下部分
And aehh, actually, it was the Japanese tour was the last one.
当然，实际上日本巡演才是最后的
I remember squaring with Jon Lord on the flight to Tokyo...
我记得在去东京的航班上和Jon Lord坐在一起
..he was pretty embarrassed and upset.
他看起来十分尴尬，难过
And, he said, "Well, sorry mate, that's the way it is."
然后，他无奈地说：”抱歉，同志。木已成舟了“
I felt really let down, actually by Jon and Paice in particular.
我十分失望，尤其是对Jon和Paice
注：真是卖队友啊
More than Ritchie strangely enough.
甚至对黑多多的失望都没有那么浓
Ritchie had always been on his own course anyway.
黑多多一直都是那么的特立独行
Ritchie said to me on the final night...
在最后一晚上，黑多多跟我说了一句
We passed on the stairs leading up to the dressing rooms
我们当时上了楼梯，去更衣室
he said, "Just want to say it's not personal, it's business."
他说：”我只想说，这不是个人问题，而是事业问题“
Then he carried on.
然后他就径直走了
Roger was let go and I stayed with the band.
Roger要求离开，我则留在了乐队
and we got in another bass player and another singer.
我们现在还得再找一个贝斯手和另一个歌手
I wanted to go more toward the melodic content area
我当时很想往旋律性的方向发展
which is what I'm doing now as well.
也就是我现在擅长的方向
It was like late '72 or even middle of '72...
好像是在1972年的秋季还是夏天的
Glenn Hughes：Deep Purple Mk3&4 贝斯手
Trapeze were playing at the Whisky a Go Go
Trapeze正在Whisky a Go Go表演
three nights or four nights.
三个晚上还是四个晚上的
I noticed, in the audience Jon Lord was there one night
有一天晚上，我看到Jon Lord
Ian Paice was there
和Ian Paice都在
Ritchie was there like, separately.
黑多多也在那，和他们若即若离
And I just figured these guys were really good fans of Trapeze
我那时就明白了他们是Trapeze的粉丝
or they were becoming fans of Trapeze:
或者正在成为Trapeze的粉丝
very vulnerable and naive back then.
现在想来，这根本站不住脚，还很幼稚
And, eh... same thing happened in The Marquee in London
然后，同样的事情也发生在伦敦的Marquee
and you know...they each came a couple of times
你也知道，他们来了好几次
And...you know... and then, you know, I had a feeling they were there for another reason.
然后，很自然地，我觉得他们来到这里的目的不是很简单
and aehh, I just didn't realise that, at that moment
反正，我当时没意识到，至少是
they were going to ask me to join.
当他们邀请我加入乐队的时候
We'd all drifted apart, personally.
我们都被冲散了，个人认为
When there were no girlfriends, everyone would
当我们没有女朋友的时候，大家都会......
and... travel together.
一起同行
and gradually I was probably the worst culprit.
也许到了最后，我成了罪魁祸首
There's no, finger pointing here
没有一个人被指着手指骂
or anyone to blame or anything like that
或者被指责之类
except maybe me.
也许除了我吧
It was...me as much as anyone, or probably more.
也许还有其他人吧，或者更多
But humm, the personal touch had gone.
无论如何，我们私下里没有交谈了
So I didn't really know that Roger was leaving
所以我当时都不知道Roger要离队了
until... it had happened on the plane home.
直到我坐飞机回家才知道
I mean, I was very pleased with the music, it was good.
说真的，我对音乐十分满意，确实很不错
I was, not in any way ashamed of it, but ahee...
我并没有为此感到羞耻，但是
I thought there was a time to add a new dimension to it
我觉得我们应该在音乐中加入新的元素
or to adopt a slightly different approach
来开辟出一条新的道路
without losing our identity
而不损失我们的独特性
but just naturally progress it.
只是很自然地进展即可
Otherwise, we'd have faded away.
要不然的话，你会被时代遗忘
and this is why and...
这就是为什么我......
Nobody really wanted to do that, so that's why we left.
没人想要那么做，但我还是决定离队
I mean, I left in, what, June?
我是说，我们是在......六月离队的？
And I think it was July or August that Billboard announced
好像是在七月还是八月的，Billboard宣布
the number one selling artists
当年销量第一的艺术家
1.Deep Purple   5.Elvis Presley   9.Led Zeppelin
10.The Rolling Stones   18.The Beatles   20.Jethro Tull
36.Pink Floyd   38.Yes   51.Marvin Gaye(What's Going On?)
60.Paul McCartney and the Wings    64.Rick Wakeman   65.The Eagles
76.Issac Hayes(Chef of the South Park)
95.Michale Jackson    98.Black Sabbath
we had two awards, number one band and number one album.
我们有两个奖项，销量第一的艺术家和销量第一的专辑
And, uh... I was in the office one day
那一天我在办公室
and I saw the billboard with the announcement and I looked at it:
我看见Billboard的公告，我定睛一看那张
a huge, great photograph showing Coverdale and Hughes.
很大的图像，上面的是Coverdale（新主唱）和Hughes（新贝斯手）
And I just went, "That's...that's really the icing on the cake.
我当时就很委屈：他们不过是沾了我的福气罢了
"That...that was my success.
这可是我亲手打造的啊
"And not only have I been kicked out of the band
而且这并不仅仅是把我给踢了出去那么简单
"but that's been taken away from me as well."
他们把我的所有成功也都夺去了
Ok... we all got watches with "Mark II" on it.
好吧，我们都看见了 "Mark II" 的成功证明
And I'm going, "Well this is nice
我就想：好吧，这确实不错
"but this surely should be Roger's watch."
但这个上面绝对应该是Roger Glover
I was getting plaques, I think I got a couple of plaques
我们拿着金唱片，我记得我拿了两张金唱片
from Who Do You Think We Are?
上面标着 Who Do You Think We Are
However, I was mature enough to realise
但是，我很成熟地意识到
that it wasn't Coverdale's fault or Glenn Hughes' fault
这个不是Coverdale和Glenn Hughes的错
any more than it was my fault when they got in Nick Simper.
更像是我的错，因为我占了Nick Simper的位置
It wasn't really uncomfortable. It was just the way it was, you know?
这个感觉并不是很好，但是生活就是曲折的，对吧
There was no point in holding grudges like that.
我觉得我拿着那些金唱片并不是很好
I think em...
我觉得呢
Ian's timing
Ian Gillan离队的时间
Ian Gillan's timing about leaving the band was terrible.
Ian Gillan离队的时间是十分不好的
I mean, the band was just on the edge
我们这个乐队正在成就
of becoming absolutely massive.
巨大成功的边缘上啊
Um... and indeed...
而且呢，确实
Burn, as an album, actually did take advantage of that
Burn，作为一张专辑，确实又给我们的名声添彩了
it's a tremendously good album, hum...
这是张十分优秀的专辑
..and the band did take that leap into stadium rock.
我们也最终到很大的运动场中开演唱会
The year before Ian left we did six American tours.
在Ian Gillan离队前，我们在美国巡演了六次
It was ridiculous.
十分火爆
And when Ian did quit, I really thought that was the end of it.
当Ian Gillan离队时，我们真觉得我们的事业结束了
And then one of our managers, John Coletta
然后我们的经纪人之一，John Coletta
showed me a copy of Billboard.
给我拿了一张Billboard表格
We had 11 different entries singles, albums, back albums.
我们有11张不同的单曲，专辑，精选集入榜
It was exploding. And that year, 1973
那销量简直是爆炸了！还有，在1973年
we were the top album-selling artists in the United States.
我们成为当年在美国最畅销的艺术家
And he said: "You can't stop now."
然后他说：“你现在不能停止”
I said: "We just did! We lost our singer and our bass player.
我反驳道：“我们刚刚结束了！我们刚刚失去了我们的主唱和贝斯手！
"How much more final can that be?"
难道我们还能有很多次结束吗？
He said: "Replace them."
他说：”找个别人“
What I'd like to say to all of you is thank you very much
我最后想说的是，我十分感谢大家的支持，你们都是好人
you've been great.
Thank you for everything you've given us in Japan
感谢你们，让我们在日本享受了一段好时光
and...this is the last night. The end.
然后，这是最后一晚了，所有的都结束了
God bless you thanks a lot.
上帝保佑你们，感谢你们
One of the reasons Made In Japan is so successful and still sells
Made In Japan十分成功，到现在仍在继续销售
and people still rate it as one of the great live albums, uhm, rock albums
大家仍然认为这是一张很伟大的现场专辑，或者说，摇滚专辑
one of the reasons for that is the brilliance of our producer
而这原因之一就是我们完美的制作人
of Martin Birch.
Martin Birch
Absolutely... under incredibly difficult conditions
是啊，在十分困难的情况下
to produce that.
去制作专辑
Hum, no, I think we'd like to try it with the track again.
额，不了，我觉得我们没必要再搞一遍那个音轨
What do you think?
你觉得呢？
Because Made In Japan had come out so well
因为Made In Japan发行得很好
I think it's regarded by a lot of people
我觉得在那时很多人都会认为
as a great live album at that point.
这是一张很伟大的现场专辑
Hum... I think it actually enhanced the album Machine Head
我认为这张专辑扩展了Machine Head的内容
because it was virtually Machine Head live on stage.
因为很明显地，这就是在舞台上表演了一遍Machine Head
I look back now only at ... it did, it exploded.
我现在来看的话......这可是相当成功了
And it was after Ian Gillan actually left
就在Ian Gillan彻底离队后
in...'73, I guess, hum...
应该是1973吧
that we became aware of the two versions of Smoke On The Water
我注意到Smoke On The Water有两个版本
both in the America top ten at the same time.
同时登上美国前十单曲榜单
I heard the live version of Smoke On The Water
我听过Smoke On The Water的现场版本
in the car, one day and... aeh... [yeah!]
记得那天是开着车听的......是啊
Live version.
现场版本
And Paice starts and Jon starts and the bass came in
Paice的鼓开始，然后是Jon的键盘，再然后贝斯开始
and I thought "Wow!"
我当时就惊呆了”WOW！“
And I suddenly felt very proud of that.
我突然间对此感到十分自豪
As simple as it is, it was exactly what was needed.
就是那么简单，就是那么自然
I originally wrote it like that, with a kind of...
我一开始是这么写的riff，有那么一种
... a kind of...
.......这么一种......
That didn't, kind of, go down with the others at the time
这个没有跟那时其他音乐一样往下走调子
注：音乐术语不太懂，有懂的请直接弹幕覆盖
so we kept it to the...
所以我们就保持这样
Here's a funny thing this is an odd thing
这件事很有趣，也很奇怪
but I've noticed that when any guitar player
但是当我见到很多其他的吉他手
goes to redo a track from Machine Head
要去重新演奏Machine Head里的曲目时
they overdo it.
他们经常过度发挥
And it's not because they're making
而这并不是他们
a mistake or anything like that.
弹错了还是怎样的
It's really because the music
确实是因为这个音乐
is so powerful
十分的有力
the memory of the music is so powerful
音乐在你的脑子里有力地回放着
that you just think you have to turn it up louder
你甚至想再将其放得更大
have more distortion or more power
再来点失真，甚至于更重
and we're often shocked when we go back to the original recordings
然后当我们重新听原版录音时
and we say; "Wow, this is actually quite delicate."
我们会说：”天啊，这个还真是精致啊“
Being a drummer, Ian Paice he was my hero, my idol.
作为一个鼓手，Ian Paice就是我的鼓手英雄，我的偶像
Chad Smith：Red Hot Chill Peppers鼓手
He was one of my first real influences
他对我的影响很大
and I listened to that record over and over.
我一遍遍地不停地听他的唱片
I always thought Made In Japan was interesting
我一直认为 Made In Japan 十分有趣
because it showed Deep Purple jamming
因为这展示出Deep Purple现场即兴
and changing the songs, changing up some of the arrangements
改变歌曲，改变一些编曲
Eddie Trunk: 电视及电台主播
and captured them on stage where a lot of people feel
然后在舞台上演出，让很多人觉得
they were absolutely lethal they did their best work
他们确实很好地展示出他们很好的作品
and it was just one of those ultimate live albums of the time.
并且这是有史以来最厉害的现场专辑之一
These guys were just in a different league
他们个个都是传奇
Deep Purple were better than everybody else.
Deep Purple 比任何乐队都要好
Hey! Thank you.
Hey! 谢谢大家
Thank you all. Thank you. Thank all very much.
谢谢，谢谢，谢谢各位观众
God bless you you've been fantastic.
上帝保佑你们，你们都太好了
Thank you for coming and we'll see you around sometime.
感谢大家观看，希望以后再见
Thank you. Thank you all for that. Thank U.
谢谢，谢谢大家，谢谢！
Deep Purple Hall of Fame:
1970-Deep Purple in Rock  英国榜第四，全球450万销量
1971-Fireball 英国榜第一，全球340万销量
1972-Machine Head 英国榜第一，美国榜第七，全球720万销量
1973-Who Do We Think We Are! 英国榜第四，全球350万销量
1972-Made in Japan 双碟专辑，全球820万销量
本片由SuperBart翻译